Everyone always says
What is Algebra? How do I use it?
But no one asks:
Why is Algebra? What does it really mean?
Maybe you've seen some Algebra before, and wondered
why?
Why are there letters? What are these symbols?
Or even if you haven't, that's completely okay. This
series of videos will focus on the intuitions behind
Algebra, and why everything is the way it is.
Perhaps we can start from the
actual name
Algebra actually comes from Arabic
and it means
the reunion of broken parts
It comes up when we want to find
the unknown.
But I think I'll just try to show you with an example:
Imagine you go to use the bathroom, but when you come back,
you see your friend with two pencils in their hand. You look
back at your pile of pencils and you only see one left.
You try to think, but forget:
how many pencils did you originally have?
This sounds like a simple problem. But instead
of trying to do it in our heads,
let's use
Algebra
Let's use a picture of the number of pencils we had like this.
We can think of this as some number that we currently don't know:
It could be 1 pencil,
4 pencils
or even 1000!
Anyways, we know that our friend took 2 of them.
So that means that our number of pencils got
subtracted by 2.
And lastly, we know that we saw
1 pencil when we got back from the bathroom.
That's why we can say that
this
is equal
to this.
So we can write our equation like this.
Overall, the number of pencils we had was subtracted by two
represented by this minus two
and now, this is
equal to 1 pencil remaining.
Think for a moment and try to understand
how we converted our word problem into Algebra.
Really, try and pause the video to contemplate.
Now, I know this doesn't seem like a lot, and it really isn't.
But the beauty with Algebra is that we can use it
to solve problems like this:
Lukas and Anna are siblings. Lukas is 3 years old. Anna is 16 years
old. How old will they be when Anna is twice as old as Lukas?
Really take a look at it, and pause the video if you want
to try it out yourself. If you try to guess, finding the answer
might take a long time! Yet, we can methodically and easily solve it
using algebra. Think of it as a sneak peek for what's to come.
Now, back to our equation, there's one
last thing I want to quickly address:
In our equation, we used a picture of a pencil to
show how many pencils we had in the first place.
But a little secret I'll tell you
right now is that mathematicians are lazy.
We wouldn't want to draw every single time we did math,
so let's use a letter instead like this.
I think p makes the most sense,
because p can stand for pencils - the amount of pencils we had.
Finally, the last thing I want to touch on is the significance of
this equals sign.
Algebra is all about trying to put back together broken
parts, which can be hard - I mean, think about
trying to put back together a broken window!
That's why we're going to be using
this, as much as we can.
Later, we'll delve into how exactly we can do that, but I hope
this served as a little intro into the wonderful world of Algebra.